<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatise of iustification Tending to proue that a sinner is iustified before God, onely by Christs righteousnes imputed. By William Bradshaw.</title>
            <author>Bradshaw, William, 1571-1618.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1615</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 92 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 61 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16621</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3529</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120447</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855644</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855644</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21145</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16621)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21145)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 702:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatise of iustification Tending to proue that a sinner is iustified before God, onely by Christs righteousnes imputed. By William Bradshaw.</title>
                  <author>Bradshaw, William, 1571-1618.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24], 96 p. : fold. table  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Creede, for William Bladon, and are to be sold at his shop, neere the great North-dore of S. Pauls Church, at the signe of the Bible,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1615.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Emmanuel College (University of Cambridge). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Justification --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21145:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21145:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TREATISE <hi>Of IVSTIFICATION.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tending to proue that a Sinner</hi> is iuſtified before God, onely by <hi>CHRISTS</hi> Righteouſnes <hi>imputed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By William Bradſhaw.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Thomas Creede,</hi> for <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Bladon,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop, neere the great North-dore of <hi>S. Pauls Church, at the ſigne of the Bible.</hi> 1615.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:21145:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <p>IMMANUEL</p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Reverendiſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> Patri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Will. Sanc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> A.C.</p>
                  <p>Coll Emman. Cant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21145:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21145:3"/>
         </div>
         <div type="list">
            <pb facs="tcp:21145:4"/>
            <head>The Method.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>In generall: of the
<list>
                           <item>Word; ſignify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to make iuſt: which is,
<list>
                                 <item>Either by Infuſion,</item>
                                 <item>Or Plea.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>Thing—
<list>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>1.</hi> What it is.</item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>2.</hi> The Ground.
<list>
                                       <item>The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, in respect
<list>
                                             <item>Of matter
<list>
                                                   <item>
                                                      <hi>1</hi>
                                                      <list>
                                                         <item>Compleat.</item>
                                                         <item>Incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat.</item>
                                                      </list>
                                                   </item>
                                                   <item>
                                                      <hi>2</hi>
                                                      <list>
                                                         <item>
                                                            <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall.</item>
                                                         <item>Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular.</item>
                                                      </list>
                                                   </item>
                                                </list>
                                             </item>
                                             <item>Of forme.
<list>
                                                   <item>
                                                      <hi>1</hi>
                                                      <list>
                                                         <item>By Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion onely.</item>
                                                         <item>By demo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                                                            <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration alſo.</item>
                                                      </list>
                                                   </item>
                                                   <item>
                                                      <hi>2</hi>
                                                      <list>
                                                         <item>In Colour,</item>
                                                         <item>In truth.</item>
                                                      </list>
                                                   </item>
                                                </list>
                                             </item>
                                          </list>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>The kindes.
<list>
                                             <item>Of perſons inherently iust.</item>
                                             <item>Otherwiſe.
<list>
                                                   <item>Meanes by ſatisfaction.
<list>
                                                         <item>by
<list>
                                                               <item>Doing.</item>
                                                               <item>ſuffering.</item>
                                                            </list>
                                                         </item>
                                                         <item>by
<list>
                                                               <item>A mans ſelfe.</item>
                                                               <item>Another.</item>
                                                            </list>
                                                         </item>
                                                      </list>
                                                   </item>
                                                   <item>The Effect, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, which is
<list>
                                                         <item>
                                                            <hi>1</hi>
                                                            <list>
                                                               <item>Plenary.</item>
                                                               <item>In part.</item>
                                                            </list>
                                                         </item>
                                                         <item>
                                                            <hi>2</hi>
                                                            <list>
                                                               <item>Meerely</item>
                                                               <item>Merited.</item>
                                                            </list>
                                                         </item>
                                                      </list>
                                                   </item>
                                                </list>
                                             </item>
                                          </list>
                                       </item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>More ſpecially. Of Iuſtification before
<list>
                           <item>GOD;
<list>
                                 <item>That it is not
<list>
                                       <item>By our owne righteouſnes.</item>
                                       <item>By Satisfaction made—
<list>
                                             <item>By our ſelues.</item>
                                             <item>By any other Creature.</item>
                                          </list>
                                       </item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>That it is by Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction made,
<list>
                                       <item>By Chriſt his
<list>
                                             <item>Fulfilling the Law.</item>
                                             <item>Suffering.</item>
                                          </list>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>For the Faithfull.</item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>Man.
<list>
                                 <item>By Man.</item>
                                 <item>By God;
<list>
                                       <item>In this life.</item>
                                       <item>At the day of Doome.</item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:21145:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21145:5"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt not be ignorant <hi>(good Reader,)</hi> what ſpeciall differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces haue bene, (and yet are) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt our ſelues in ſom points, about the <hi>Iuſtification of a Sinner before GOD.</hi> Whence manie weake mindes haue bene ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what perplexed, &amp; ſome ſtrong ones (at leaſt in their own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits) exceedingly diſtempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; as though there were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs which ouer-turned Foundations, teaching blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Hereſies about this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: whereas all of vs with one
<pb facs="tcp:21145:6"/> mouth profeſſe this, <hi>That a Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner is Iustified, not by any Formall inherent Righteouſnes in himſelfe, but onely by the free &amp; meere grace and mercie of GOD, through the meritorious Satisfaction of our SA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>IOVR CHRIST, the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Mediatour betweene God and a Sinner.</hi> Wherein we all giue all the glory of our Iuſtification &amp; Saluation to God in Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, and therein hold the maine Foundation. We differ onely in certaine Circumſtances, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in nothing is derogated, eyther from the mercie of God, or me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites of Chriſt, or arrogated to our owne workes.</p>
            <p>Some of vs hold, that a Sinner is iuſtified by the vertue &amp; me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites both of Chriſts actiue and paſſiue Obedience imputed. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therſome, by the merites of his paſſiue obedience imputed, but
<pb facs="tcp:21145:6"/> not of his Actiue. A third ſort, by the merits both of his actiue and paſſiue, but not imputed.</p>
            <p>The firſt, giues all to Chriſt, but equally diuides the vertue, betweene his actiue and paſſiue righteouſnes. The ſecond giues no leſſe to him: only that which it takes from the actiue, it giues ſuperabundantly to the paſſiue.</p>
            <p>The thirde, giues as much to Chriſt, as eyther of the other, derogating nothing from the vertue, eyther of the actiue or paſſiue, but denying only a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall manner of Application.</p>
            <p>The firſt of theſe opinions hath bin, &amp; (for ought I know) is moſt generally receiued, &amp; is that which ſeemes moſt <hi>Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxall,</hi> &amp; which in this Treatiſe I deſire to maintain. If in ſome fewe paſſages, I goe out of that beaten tracke, which they haue
<pb facs="tcp:21145:7"/> kept, who before me haue main<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tained this truth, it is not from any affectation of ſingularitie; For I neuer held it ſafe, nor any credite to walke alone, in any matter of Religion, any further then meere neceſſitie, and iuſt <hi>Apologie</hi> requires: but becauſe ſome partes of the way, which they goe, lyes ouer ſuch hills, as I am not able to climbe, I ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore haue ben forced ſomtimes to goe ſomewhat aſide, that I might the better come againe into the way, where it lies in the plaine.</p>
            <p>For the other two opinions, (with due reuerence, reſerued to the maintainers of them; whome I acknowledge to bee great learned and worthie Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines) I thinke them ſomewhat erroneous; but withall, to haue riſen from two poſitions (to my
<pb facs="tcp:21145:7"/> ſeeming) as erroneous, held or granted by ſome (if not all) who haue maintained the firſt.</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>That Christ by the merites of his Paſſiue obedience onely, hath freed vs from the guilt of all ſinne, both actuall and, originall, of Omiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and Commiſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>That in the imputation of Chriſts Obedience both Actiue and Paſſiue, God doeth ſo beholde and conſider a Sinner in Chriſt, as if the Sinner himſelfe had done &amp; ſuffered, thoſe very Particulars which Christ did, and ſuffered for him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt of theſe, is the very ground and Foundation of the ſecond opinion: which beeing graunted, I cannot (as yet) ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e how it can be auoided, but that wee muſt holde the ſame. For what more can be required, to the Iuſtification of a ſinner, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be freed, and expiated of all
<pb facs="tcp:21145:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſinnes whatſoeuer, not onely of Commiſſion, but Omiſſion?</p>
            <p>Can a man poſſibly bee more iuſtified, then ſo to be freed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all ſinne &amp; fault, as to be eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and iudged as one that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer committed any euil forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, &amp; neuer omitted any good required? Doth Chriſts actiue Righteouſnes according to the Lawe conſiſt in any thing elſe, but in the leauing vndone of whatſoeuer euill forbidden, and in the doing of all good things commanded? What then auay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the imputation of this, when ſo much is granted to be obtained by the other? If ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee will firmely maintaine the firſt Opinion, I cannot ſee, but wee muſt needs forgoe this firſt Poſition, and holde</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That to the very Expiation of ſinne, and the Freeing from the guilte
<pb facs="tcp:21145:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> hereof, the imputattion both of the Actiue and Paſſiue righteouſnes of Chriſt are neceſſarie, and that the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne is not to bee ſeparated from the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>her.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond Poſition taketh <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mputation</hi> in ſuch a ſtrict ſenſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s ſeemes not neceſſarie; For both the Actiue &amp; Paſſiue righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes of Chriſt, may be ſaid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o bee imputed to a ſinner, if God (without any further co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration) but accept that which Chriſt hath done and ſuffred, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ful ſatisfaction, for that which a ſinner ſhould haue done, or ſuffted in his owne perſon: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that it ſeems to take away all neceſsity of the imputation of Chriſts Suffrings. For if God repute Chriſtes fulfilling of the Lawe, to be euery ſinners fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the Law, then in his ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling thereof, is euery ſuch ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb facs="tcp:21145:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> (to whom it is in ſuch a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner imputed) perfectly righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. If perfectly righteous, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly Iuſtifiable, what needes then Chriſt moreouer, eyther to Suffer for the Iuſtification of a ſinner, or a ſinner to be repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to Suffer in Chriſt, to any ſuch ende?</p>
            <p>This other poſition, (as I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue) hath giuen occaſion of the third Opinion. The Author thereof, (a very Learned, Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend, and Iudicious Diuine) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying all Imputation, both of the Actiue and Paſſiue righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of Chriſt (as farre as I can learne,) onely in the ſtrict ſenſe aforeſaide, and that (as it ſeemes to mee,) vppon good ground, as may appeare further ſomewhat in this Treatiſe.</p>
            <p>Our differences then (bleſſed be God,) are not ſo great, but
<pb facs="tcp:21145:9"/> there is both poſſibilitie, and hope of Reconciliation, and no ſuch cauſe of any fiery Oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions one againſt an other; eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially, ſeeing that they who heerein are out of the way, may ſeeme to haue beene put out thereof, onely by the blockes, that our ſelues have layde ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. I take not vpon mee to bee a Moderator between ſo many Learned men of all ſides, or to ſee further then they, into ſo great a Myſterie.</p>
            <p>If in ſome pety Circumſtances I haue diſcouered that which they haue ouerſeene, it is not ſo much for want of any ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of ſight in them, as for that they haue not ſtouped ſo lowe as I haue done: It beeing not ſtrange for them that look high eſt, and ſee furtheſt, to ouer-ſee much; and not vnvſuall for
<pb facs="tcp:21145:10"/> thoſe who are ſtanders by, (though ſimple in compariſon) to ſee ſome things, which the cunningeſt Gameſters ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ouerſee.</p>
            <p>I firſt penned this Treatiſe to teach my ſelfe, and haue herein oppoſed my ſelf as much as any man elſe, as may wel be known to ſome, who knowe what I haue formerly helde.</p>
            <p>After, for my further Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction and information, I cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed diuers Copies thereof to be written forth, and communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them to ſundrie Reuerend and learned Diuines, ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the ſame to their cenſures; from whome I receiued (out of their loue) diuers materiall A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimaduerſions, and doubtes: which thogh they haue not bin of force to moue mee to change my mind in any material point,
<pb facs="tcp:21145:10"/> yet haue made me explane mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rs more fully, then otherwiſe ſhould haue thought had bin <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>edfull. Yet if herein I haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot ſatisfied them, or any elſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hey ſhall binde me vnto them, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> they will bee pleaſed further <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o animaduert, and obiect a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ainſt ſuch Particulars, where <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hey ſhall reſt vnſatisfied.</p>
            <p>That it dares thus boldly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ome foorth in publique, it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot ſo much from any hearte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing it hath had from mee, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hrough ſome priuate encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>agements from others, farre more Learned and Iudicious then my ſelfe; whome thou muſt blame, if it proue of no vſe to the Church of God.</p>
            <p>The world I know hath long <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>roaned vnder the multitude of Books, and yet ſtill it deſires and calls for for more; The beſt
<pb facs="tcp:21145:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> is, this Booke is of ſo little b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>den, that it can haue no m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſenſe of it, then an Elepha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> though neuer ſo loaded, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> haue of a Flye, that ſits vpp it.</p>
            <p>I haue ſaid no more of <hi>Fai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> then was needfull for the v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derſtanding of the nature of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtification,</hi> and of that force a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vſe that it hath therein; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> rather, for that it deſerue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Treatiſe of it ſelfe, which (b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for ſome diſtractions) I had a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tempted before now: yet I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther deſire that ſome other more ſufficient, would take out of my hand, and take th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> alſo from my hand, and poli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it, as the excellencie of the <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gument</hi> requires, then whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> certainly there is not (among all the heads of Diuinitie) a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> one more neceſſary, profitabl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:21145:11"/> or comfortable, eſpecially, to afflicted and humbled Sinners.</p>
            <p>Thus praying thee to pardon my great boldneſſe, and to take in good part this poore <hi>Eſſay,</hi> and where I may ſeeme to erre, to helpe me by thy prayers, and other meanes into the way; I bid thee Farewell in Chriſt. <hi>New-hall, April.</hi> 8. 1615.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine, W. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:21145:12"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21145:12"/>
            <head>THE ARGVMENTS of the ſeuerall Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>1.</hi> Of the Signification of the Worde.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2.</hi> What Iuſtification is.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3.</hi> Of the degrees of Iuſtification.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4.</hi> Of Iustification, by inherent Righteouſnes.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5.</hi> Of the Iuſtification of thoſe, who are not inherently Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6.</hi> Of Satisfaction in Generall.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>7.</hi> Of Satisfaction in ſpeciall.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>8.</hi> Of Pardon.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>9.</hi> Of Iuſtification before God.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>10.</hi> That no man is Righteous or iuſtifiable in Gods ſight, by the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes of the Law, or by his owne inherent righteouſnes.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:21145:13"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>11.</hi> That no man can make ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction for his owne, or an other mans ſinne.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>12.</hi> That no other meere Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, can make ſatisfaction for the ſinne of Man.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>13.</hi> That the Sonne of God hath made Satisfaction for the ſinnes of all them that ſhall be iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>14.</hi> Of the pardon of ſinne, and our Adoption.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>15.</hi> Of Iuſtifying Faith.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>16.</hi> Of Iuſtification before men.</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:21145:13"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:21145:14"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:21145:14"/>
            <head>OF IVSTIFICATION.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>THE I. CHAPTER.</hi> Of the ſignification of the Word.</head>
               <p n="1">1 THE <hi>Latine Iuſtifice</hi> (of which our <hi>Engliſh</hi> word <hi>To iuſtifie</hi> is deriued) is not to bee founde in <hi>Tully, Caeſar, Terence,</hi> or any other the auncient and pureſt Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of the Latine tongue<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but was made ſince by Latine Diuines, to expreſſe that which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s vniuerſally meant by the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and the <hi>Greeke</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. All which, eſpecially
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:21145:15"/> the <hi>Hebrew</hi> and <hi>Latine</hi> (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Notation of the words) doe ſign<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fie <hi>to make iuſt:</hi> As, <hi>to purifie,</hi> ſignifies to make pure: to <hi>ſanctifie,</hi> to make holy, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="2">2 One may be ſayd in ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary form of ſpeech <hi>To be made iust,</hi> two manner of waies: by <hi>Infuſion</hi> or <hi>Plea.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3 By infuſion, when the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, habit, or vertue of Iuſtice is by any kinde of meanes, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally put into, procured or effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in any perſon, whether by his owne act, or by anothers, whether in whole, or in any part or degree, whether immediatly ingenerated, or created in that ſubiect, in which it ſubſiſteth, or powred into it, as wine into an emptie veſſell; or whether mediatly gotten, as learning by the precept of the Maſter, or
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:21145:15"/> health by the potion of the Phyſitian; ſtrength, actiuitie, or any other habite of body or minde by exerciſe, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="4">4 After this manner was <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam made iust</hi> in the firſt Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. In the ſame manner are they in ſome degree <hi>made iust,</hi> who are regenerated and ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified, and who by the Word and Sacraments, and other meanes and exerciſes of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, do grow and increaſe in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe and righteouſnes. And in this ſenſe the Wiſeman ſpeaks, <hi>Eccle.</hi> 7.29. <hi>Lo, this onely haue I found, that God made man iust; but they haue ſought many inuentions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5 They who are in any ſuch manner <hi>made iuſt,</hi> are (as the Schooles vſe to ſpeake) formal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly iuſt, or iuſt by righteouſnes inherent.</p>
               <p n="6">6 Though <hi>to make iuſt,</hi> in the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:21145:16"/> ſenſe aforeſaid be moſt proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>to make iust:</hi> yet to <hi>Iuſtifie,</hi> eyther in our Engliſh, or the Latine tongue, (eyther in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon vſe, or any approoued Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor) doth not ſignifie, <hi>to make iust</hi> in any ſuch ſenſe: no more (for ought yet hath beene ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed to the contrarie) doth the <hi>Hebrew</hi> or the <hi>Greeke</hi> worde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid.</p>
               <p n="7">7 To <hi>bee made iuſt by Plea,</hi> is, when the Iuſtice of any perſon, any waies queſtioned, is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted &amp; diſcouered, by words or other meanes equiualent thereunto. Hence, as we ſay of thoſe, who charge and accuſe a man of any act of villanie, hee makes him a knaue or a villaine: So contrarily wee ſay of him, who hath pleaded a perſons in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocencie, that is accuſed or charged, hee hath made him an
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:21145:16"/> honeſt man. Hence in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, as they are ſayd, <hi>To take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the righteouſnes of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, which accuſe or condemne the innocent,</hi> Eſa. 5.23: So may they by the ſame forme of ſpeech be ſaid<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> 9.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>to giue righteouſnes,</hi> which pleade for, and excuſe thoſe which are any waies charged or accuſed, whether iuſtly or vniuſtly.</p>
               <p n="8">8 Though to <hi>bee made iuſt</hi> in this ſenſe, be not ſo properly to <hi>be made iuſt,</hi> as in the former; yet in this ſenſe vſually &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly, is the<note n="(b)" place="margin">I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtifica<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> Latine, and our Engliſh word to <hi>Iuſtifie</hi> vſed, ſo alſo are the <hi>Greeke</hi> and <hi>Hebrew</hi> wordes aforeſaide. Therefore <hi>Grammarians</hi> interpret <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, by <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. i. To eſteeme and iudge one to bee righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. See <hi>Heſychius</hi> and <hi>Suidas</hi> on this word.</p>
               <p n="9">
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:21145:17"/>9 Though therfore the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation aforeſaid, doe indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently fauour either, and more the former; yet for the true meaning and ſignification of words, the common vſe is more to be regarded then that which ſounds from the Notation.</p>
               <p n="10">10 The <hi>Hebrew</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> (which properly ſignifies Lawes or ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes) the old Interpreter vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally tranſlates (though barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly) <hi>Iustificationes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r. ell. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uſtif. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>p. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ct. 2.</note> Iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.4.8. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But it cannot be proued, that ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they are ſo called, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect that <hi>they make</hi> the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>iuſt</hi> in the firſt ſenſe; but rather becauſe, after that a man is <hi>made iuſt</hi> by them in the firſt ſenſe, they are meanes to defend, and maintaine and war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant that Iuſtice, and ſo are a meanes to make them <hi>iuſt</hi> in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:21145:17"/> this latter ſenſe; It being a good Plea, that a man is iuſt, when it may bee auouched againſt any that takes exception, that that which hee hath done is accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Gods Statutes.</p>
               <p n="11">11 Hence alſo the Law in generall is ſaid to iuſtifie thoſe who are or ſhall bee righteous, according thereunto: not in this reſpect, that in and through the obſeruance thereof, a man is formally, or inherently righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous; but when being formally iuſt and righteous thereby, hee is by the ſame acquitted and freede from iniuſtice: As when a Iudge ſhall execute a Malefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor according to the Lawes of the State, the ſaid Lawes make him not iuſt, in the firſt ſenſe; but they only <hi>iuſtifie</hi> the Iudge, and ſo <hi>make him iuſt</hi> in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond ſenſe, when they ſhall
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:21145:18"/> warrant and diſcharge him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the charge and imputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of iniuſtice in that action.</p>
               <p n="12">12 Though by teaching and inſtructing,<note place="margin">Contr. Bell. de Iuſt. li. 2. cap. 3. Sect. 9.</note> Miniſters may bee ſayde, to bee inſtruments and meanes of making men formal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and inherently iuſt in ſome degree: yet it followeth not, that in that reſpect they are ſaid to <hi>Iustifie, Dan.</hi> 12.3. But they may be ſayde rather to iuſtifie, as they are meanes and inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to bring men to beleeue in Chriſt, wherby they are iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and ſo <hi>made righteous</hi> in the other ſenſe. In the ſame reſpect Miniſters are ſaide to ſaue, and to binde and looſe: 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.16. <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.18. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 20.23.</p>
               <p n="13">
                  <note place="margin">Contr. Bell. ibid. Sect. 16.</note>13 Where it is ſayd, <hi>Reu.</hi> 22. <hi>Let him that is iuſt, be iuſtified ſtill;</hi> Wee are not neceſſarily to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand thereby, Let him ſtill
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:21145:18"/> be made iuſt, or ſtill proceede to bee made iuſt by inherent righteouſnes. But let him ſtill, more and more continue, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare and ſhew himſelfe iuſt, which is to <hi>make iuſt</hi> in this lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſenſe.</p>
               <p n="14">14 That may bee graunted therfore which <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith;<note place="margin">Contr. Bell. ibid. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ct. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>That he that iuſtifies a wicked man, makes him of a wicked man, a iuſt man.</hi> In <hi>Pſal.</hi> 3O. <hi>That by the grace of GOD wee are iuſtified.</hi> i. <hi>Made iust: Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de peccato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum meritis &amp; remiſſ. cap.</hi> 33. <hi>That to bee iuſtified, is nothing elſe but to be made iuſt: Lib. de ſpirit. &amp; lit. cap.</hi> 26. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And yet it will not follow thence, that he held, that to <hi>iuſtifie</hi> ſignifieth to <hi>make iuſt,</hi> by formall and inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent righteouſnes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:21145:19"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>THE II. CHAP.</hi> Of Iustification in generall what it is.</head>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>I<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>stification</hi> therefore (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the vniuerſall vſe of the word) is the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring of a perſon that is accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed or ſuſpected of a fault, and in that regard obnoxious to blame or puniſhment, to bee righteous and iuſt: and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently vnworthy eyther the one or the other; <hi>Deut.</hi> 25.1. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 43.9. <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.19. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.4. <hi>Pro.</hi> 17.15. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 5.23. <hi>&amp;</hi> 50.8 <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.3.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Where one is not queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned for, nor ſo much as ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted of any fault, there Iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation hath no place: yea, in ſuch a caſe to iuſtifie a perſon, is
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:21145:19"/> commonly reputed, a ſecret ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation and condemnation of him. And if the party charged or ſuſpected, be no way liable to blame or puniſhment in that reſpect, the iuſtification of ſuch a one ſeemes needleſſe and end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Though therefore out of theſe caſes, there may be a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of Iuſtice: yet we ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vſe to call any ſuch declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by the name of Iuſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but by the generall name of prayſe or commendation.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Hence, if <hi>Adam</hi> had not ſinned, and if there had beene no Diuels to haue charged him with ſinne, nor any ground or colour to ſuſpect him of ſinne, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ugh hee might in this caſe, to his prayſe and commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, haue beene declared and pronounced to bee iuſt and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent:
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:21145:20"/> yet he could not ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in properly be ſaid to be <hi>iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi> When a father declares the vertue &amp; goodnes of his childe to a ſtranger, who neither knowes good, nor ſuſpects e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill by him, wee vſe to ſay, hee praiſeth and commendeth his childe: but we neuer ſay, hee iuſtifies him, but in caſe of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation and charge. Though therefore there can be no Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication without a declaration of righteouſnes: yet that may be, where there neyther is, nor needes to be any Iuſtification.</p>
               <p n="5">5 Hence alſo God and Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome are ſaid to bee iuſtified, not as often as they are praiſed and extolled, or their righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes meerely declared; but ſo far forth onely as their waies and works are declared to bee iuſt &amp; free from blame, againſt
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:21145:20"/> the conceits &amp; charges of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men, who vſe by ſome meanes or other, to make them vniuſt, and when by meanes of ſuch a declaration, they are vindicated from diſhonour. <hi>Rom:</hi> 3.3.4. <hi>Matth:</hi> 11.19. <hi>Luk:</hi> 7.35.</p>
               <p n="6">6 <hi>Iuſtification</hi> therefore, in ſubſtance, is the ſame with <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pologie</hi> or defence.</p>
               <p n="7">7 So to declare ones Iuſtice, as to declare not onely that he is free from blame, but alſo worthie of a reward, is more then to iuſtifie.</p>
               <p n="8">8 It is not of the eſſence of Iuſtification, that it be done in publike iudgement, but it may be indifferently, eyther in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate or publicke, and may bee performed, either by the partie himſelfe, that is queſtioned or ſuſpected, or by another, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:21145:21"/> Friend, Witnes, Aduocate, or Iudge.</p>
               <p n="9">9 The immediate end of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification, is ſo farre forth to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moue the blot and aſperſion of Iniuſtice from a perſon, that he may be freed (as much as in the power of the Iuſtifier lies) from blame, puniſhment, or reproch.</p>
               <p n="10">10 The proper matter of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification, is Iuſtice or Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie, not cauſed or produced by the acte of Iuſtification, but exiſting ſome way or other be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. For a perſon is not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore iuſt, becauſe he is iuſtified; but he is therefore iuſtified, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee is <hi>iust:</hi> the iuſtice of the partie iuſtified, beeing the cauſe of his iuſt fication, and not his iuſtification the cauſe of his Iuſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce.</p>
               <p n="11">11 The Forme is the pleading of the ſaid righteouſnes or inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:21145:21"/> in the caſes aforeſpoken.</p>
               <p n="12">12 One vſuall and ſpeciall effect thereof, is <hi>Reconciliation;</hi> which is a pacification of that partie, who is, or may be (vpon conceit of fault done) prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked to diſlike, blame, or puniſh. And in this reſpect (according to the iudgement of reuerend and learned Diuines) may <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification</hi> be ſaide to be a part of <hi>Reconciliation,</hi> though not ſo properly; onſidering that there may be <hi>Iuſtification,</hi> where there is no <hi>Reconciliation,</hi> and <hi>Reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation,</hi> where there is no <hi>Iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</hi> And therefore <hi>Iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> cannot bee any ſuch mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber or part therof, as doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute the ſame, except it be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in a larger ſenſe, then the common vſe of the worde ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth vnto.</p>
               <p n="13">13 Contrary to <hi>Iuſtification,</hi>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:21145:22"/> is<note n="(a)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Pro:</hi> 17.5. <hi>Eſa:</hi> 5.23. &amp; 50.8. <hi>Rom:</hi> 8.33.</note> Condemnation, Accuſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Slander, Calumniation, Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, and ſuch like; againſt one or other of which, <hi>Iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> alwayes fighteth; and in the remoueall of which, the ſpeciall vſe thereof conſiſteth,</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. Of the Degrees of <hi>Iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation in generall.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1 IN <hi>Iuſtification</hi> we are to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, Firſt, the Degrees, then the kindes.</p>
               <p n="2">2 The Degrees bee diuers. Some, in regard of the matter of <hi>Iuſtification;</hi> Other ſome in regard of the <hi>Forme.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3 In regard of the <hi>Matter,</hi> Firſt, <hi>Iuſtification</hi> is either com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:21145:22"/> or incompleat.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Compleat, when there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by a partie is declared to bee throughly and fully freed, from the faulte that is charged vpon him, and all the degrees therof.</p>
               <p n="5">5 Incompleat, when the partie is not fully cleared, but when by Circumſtances the fault is onely in ſome degree, leſſened, mitigated, and excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</p>
               <p n="6">6 Heerevnto may bee redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced <hi>Iuſtification,</hi> by compariſon; which is, when a perſon is not ſimply declared, to be righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, but onely in compariſon of others, who haue had more meanes, to make them righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. Thus is <hi>Samaria</hi> ſaid to be iuſtified by <hi>Ieruſalem, Ezek:</hi> 16.51.</p>
               <p n="7">7 Such a comparatiue <hi>Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication,</hi> is after a ſort, Metapho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricall
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:21145:23"/> only. For as in perfect and true Iuſtification, a man that before might ſeeme faultie, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares then free from fault: So thoſe who are in truth guiltie, when they are compared with thoſe, who are worſe, by means thereof, their faultes eyther ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare the leſſe, or not at all; As great lights ſo darken and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure the leſſer, that they ſeeme to extinguiſh them; and are commonly ſaide to extinguiſh them. But yet tropically; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe during that time, they are as lights extinguiſhed.</p>
               <p n="8">8 Secondly, <hi>Iuſtification</hi> in reſpect of the matter may be v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſall or particular.</p>
               <p n="9">9 Vniuerſall, when a partie is declared, to bee free from all ſorts, &amp; degrees of faults what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer. <hi>Rom:</hi> 8.33.</p>
               <p n="10">10 Particular, when one is
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:21145:23"/> declared to be free, from ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rticular faults onely, as hee is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>arged with, or ſuſpected for, now guilty ſoeuer he may both be, and be knowne to bee, of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther faults not queſtioned. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 7.3.4.5. <hi>Luk.</hi> 20.14.15.</p>
               <p n="11">11 The firſt of theſe is called by our Diuines, the Iuſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the perſon; the other the Iuſtification of the cauſe, thogh in truth the perſon is iuſtified in both; in the one abſolutely, in the other reſpectiuely. And to ſpeake properly, that onely is the Iuſtification of the cauſe, whereby a Particular cauſe, that is accuſed, or thought to be naught, is pleaded to bee good and iuſt. And the maine end of ſuch a iuſtification alſo, doeth not ſo much reſpect the cauſe it ſelfe, as the perſon whoſe it is; The cauſe beeing
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:21145:24"/> iuſtified, that thereby the pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eſpecially, whoſe cauſe it may be iuſtified, who is iud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> faultie, till the particular ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be freed from fault.</p>
               <p n="12">12 Iuſtification in reſpec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Forme, may bee eyther Aſſertion onely, or by Dem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtration alſo.</p>
               <p n="13">13 By Aſſertion only, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> a partie is onely nakedly p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nounced, or with Aſſeuerat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> or oath alſo, affirmed to be f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> from fault.</p>
               <p n="14">14 Either of theſe is ſuffi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ent, where the credite of h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> that iuſtifieth is without i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> exception. Otherwiſe, thog<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> haue the name, yet is it as go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> as no iuſtification.</p>
               <p n="15">15 Iuſtification by Demo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtration alſo, is, when by ſuffi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ent proofs and other argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the innocencie of any perſon
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:21145:24"/> eui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nced, and thereby the accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> or ſurmiſers conuicted of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or or malice.</p>
               <p n="16">16 This degree of Iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>on is ſufficient, bee the partie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t iuſtifieth neuer ſo ſubiect exception, or (as wee ſay) racked in credit.</p>
               <p n="17">17 Furthermore, Iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>on alſo in reſpect of Forme, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ay be eyther in colour onely, in truth.</p>
               <p n="18">18. In colour only, when by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ophiſtication, colluſion, aequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>cation, &amp;c. faultes are excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, leſſened, or made no faults. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o:</hi> 17.15. &amp; 24.24. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 23.20.</p>
               <p n="19">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>9 This manner or degree of <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſtification,</hi> (vnworthily ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d) is of no force, but with ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nde of perſons, as may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ded. And therfore it is called <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſtification,</hi> becauſe with ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nde of perſons, it vſually pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:21145:25"/> the ſame effects th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Iuſtification doth, at leaſt t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the fraud and error be diſcou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red.</p>
               <p n="20">20 Iuſtification in truth, when that which is done, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſaid herein, is in truth and ſy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceritie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IIII.</hi> Of Iuſtification by inherent righteouſnes.</head>
               <p n="1">1 HItherto of the degree of <hi>Iuſtification;</hi> the kin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> follow. And it is eithe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of perſons inherently iuſt, or o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>therwiſe.</p>
               <p n="2">2 The Iuſtification of a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon inherently iuſt, is when th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Non-commiſſion</hi> of a fault that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> charged, is directly pleaded.</p>
               <p n="3">3 This is done by ſhewing
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:21145:25"/> either that he did not that fault which hee is charged with, or that that which hee is charged with as a fault, is no fault; 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.10.12. <hi>Ier.</hi> 26.15.16.</p>
               <p n="4">4 They who are iuſtified af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this manner, are iuſtified by their owne workes and merits. For they who are founde inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, and free from commiſſion of fault, according to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree thereof, haue a righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of their owne: and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes meriteth iuſtification.</p>
               <p n="5">5 This kinde of Iuſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is not a making iuſt by inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent righteouſnes, but a decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring iuſt, for inherent righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:21145:26"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Of the Iuſtification of thoſe who are not inherently righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous.</head>
               <p n="1">1 THe Iuſtification of ſuch as are not inherently righteous, is when the fault that is charged, is acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged, and ſatisfaction plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</p>
               <p n="2">2 No mortall man can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe any other means by which ſuch a perſon ſhould bee iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Where a fault committed is not acknowledged, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed or denied, there the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie cannot bee ſaid to be iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed whatſoeuer elſe may bee pleaded for him.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Though the fault bee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:21145:26"/> and confeſſed: yet it is not ſufficient to Iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, except ſatisfaction alſo can be pleaded.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> Of Satisfaction in generall.</head>
               <p n="1">1 SAtisfaction is, when ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient amends is made to the party offended for the fault done, by meanes whereof, free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome from puniſhment is me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited, and the fault thereby af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a ſort extinguiſhed.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Sufficient amends is then made, when the offended par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, or his Subſtitute, reapeath as much benefit, at leaſt, as hee ſhould haue done if the fault had not beene committed.</p>
               <p n="3">3 This Satisfaction, being of the ſame merite with righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes,
<pb facs="tcp:21145:27"/> muſt needes bee eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med for righteouſnes. Hence hee that can plead ſuch an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends, is to be reputed as if he had not committed the fault, and by conſequent, after a ſort iuſt or righteous.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Sometimes the partie of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended may accept for ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction that which doeth not make eyther full amends, or any amends for the fault done: yea, hee may ſometimes accept of a bare acknowledgement of a fault, or of promiſe of amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the time preſent or to come, as ſatisfaction: but the pleading of ſuch a reputed ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction is not to iuſtifie.</p>
               <p n="5">5 Hence, where a fault is of that nature, and hath done a hurt of that kinde, that no ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient amends can bee made, there the partie guiltie hath no
<pb facs="tcp:21145:27"/> meanes to bee iuſtified.</p>
               <p n="6">6 Such a ſatisfaction once made, the partie is to bee eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med as blameleſſe, as if hee had not treſpaſſed at all: for, hauing made full amends, he is free in that regard from deſert of euill. And hee that is free from deſert of euill, is in the ſame regard (and that deſeruedly) to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted blameleſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> Of Satisfaction in ſpeciall.</head>
               <p n="1">1 SAtisfaction may be made eyther by doing or ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring; or by both.</p>
               <p n="2">2 That doing or ſuffering is of no force to ſatisfie which is due by bond, though the partie offending had committed no fault at all; it being ridiculous to account the payment of one
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:21145:28"/> debt for the diſcharge of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Satisfaction alſo may bee made eyther by the partie him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, or by another; or partly by himſelfe, and partly by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p n="4">4 So farre foorth as any are iuſtified by ſatisfaction made by themſelues, they are no leſſe iuſtified by their owne merits and works, then they who ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer offended: thoſe ſatisfacto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry acts of theirs being aequiua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent in merite to that Iuſtice which by the fault committed they were depriued of.</p>
               <p n="5">5 He may be ſaid after a ſort to ſatisfie in his owne perſon by ſuffering, who can pleade that the partie offended hath committed the ſame, or an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall, or greater fault againſt him.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:21145:28"/>6 Satisfaction made by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that which is done, or ſuffered by another, is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted for that which ought to haue beene done or ſuffered by the offender himſelfe.</p>
               <p n="7">7 This may bee eyther by doing or ſuffering the ſame kinde of things that the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ought to haue done; or ſuch things as are of another kinde, if of the ſame worth and value.</p>
               <p n="8">8 Some things done by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother may ſatisfie for the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender, which if they were done by the offender himſelf, would adde offence to offence: for ſome things done by ſome may bee ſatisfactorie and meritori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, which done by otherſome are vnlawfull and impious.</p>
               <p n="9">9 Some things done by the offender himſelfe may bee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to ſatisfie, which done
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:21145:29"/> by another may abundantly ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie. And ſome alſo done by the offender may more then ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie, which done by ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, either doe not, or doe but ſatisfie.</p>
               <p n="10">10 That ſatisfaction which is made by another doeth the more iuſtifie, the more wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and the leſſe able the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender is to ſatisfie for himſelfe.</p>
               <p n="11">11 It is all one to be iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the ſatisfaction, or me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, or righteouſnes of another; ſeeing nothing ſatisfieth, but that which meriteth; and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing meriteth, but righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
               <p n="12">12 To bee iuſtified in this manner, is not to bee iuſtified by any works, merits, or righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes of a mans owne, but by anothers.</p>
               <p n="13">13 So faire foorth then as a
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:21145:29"/> man is iuſtified by ſatisfaction made by another, hee is alſo made iuſt by the Iuſtice of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other.</p>
               <p n="14">14 To be made iuſt by the Iuſtice of another, is to be iuſt by Imputation; it being not poſſible for any to bee iuſt, by anothers Iuſtice, but by Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</p>
               <p n="15">15 This imputation is the accounting and accepting of another mans Iuſtice, for that Iuſtice which ſhould bee in the partie himſelfe.</p>
               <p n="16">16 It is not neceſſarie, that that which is imputed to the iuſtification of another, ſhould be reputed as done by him that is iuſtified. But it ſufficeth to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, if that which is done bee eſteemed, and in regard of that eſtimatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, be accepted of, as equal in worth, and merit, to
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:21145:30"/> that which the iuſtified perſon ſhould haue done in his owne perſon.</p>
               <p n="17">17. The ſatisfaction of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, cannot be imputed, to the Iuſtification of an offender; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the treſpas of the offender, be after a ſort imputed to him: As he that diſchargeth another mans debt, is in that regard ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted and eſteemed, to bee the debter.</p>
               <p n="18">18 Hence, as hee that ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth for another is righteous in himſelf, but vnrighteous by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation onely: So hee that by this means is iuſtified, is vnrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous in himſelf, and righteous by imputation onely; he being in the ſame manner iuſt, as hee that ſatisfieth is euill.</p>
               <p n="19">19 To hold therefore, that a man can in no ſorte, or ſenſe, be iuſt, by another mans Iuſtice; is
<pb facs="tcp:21145:30"/> to holde, That one cannot haue any benefite, by anothers ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action, or that one cannot me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite for an other: which well conſidered, will be found to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrowe the maine foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all Chriſtianitie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPT. VIII. <hi>Of Pardon.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1 THe ſpeciall fruit of that Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification, which is by Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, if it be effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, is <hi>Pardon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>Pardon</hi> is the remitting of an euill, or puniſhment, deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by an offence.</p>
               <p n="3">3 That Pardon is ridiculous, wherein the faulte is forgiuen, but not the puniſhment; euen as ridiculous, as one ſhould ſay; Hee forgiues the debt, but not
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:21145:31"/> the payment of the debt, there being no other meanes to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue and pardon a fault, but by remitting the puniſhment due thereunto.</p>
               <p n="4">4 There may be ſatisfaction, where there is no pardon, and pardon where there is neyther ſatisfaction, nor any manner of Iuſtification. <hi>Pſal:</hi> 7.8. and 17. 1. &amp; 26.1. &amp; 139.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. &amp; <hi>Gen:</hi> 50.17-22.</p>
               <p n="5">5 Pardon therefore is ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the whole, nor any eſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all part of Iuſtification, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a <hi>contingent</hi> effect thereof.</p>
               <p n="6">6 Pardon may be eyther ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie, or in part.</p>
               <p n="7">7 <hi>Plenarie,</hi> when all partes and degrees of puniſhment are remitted.</p>
               <p n="8">8 That is, when the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der is in no worſe eſtate or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, then he ſhould haue bin
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:21145:31"/> in, if he had not offended. For ſo long as hee lyes vnder any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of euill, whether da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mage or paine, which he had bin free from, if he had not offended, he cannot be ſaid, to be fully par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned.</p>
               <p n="9">9 He is reputed, to be in no worſe condition, then hee was before; who though he remain vnder ſome degree of euill, which hee ſhould haue bin free from, if hee had not offended, and ſhall neuer bee reſtored a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, to the ſame eſtate he was in before; yet hath that euill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenſed, either with greater certaintie of that good, which hee preſently enioyeth, though not ſo great as the former: or with ſure titles and vndoubted poſſibilities of better things to come.</p>
               <p n="10">10 Pardon in part, is when
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:21145:32"/> ſome degrees only, and not the entier puniſhment is remitted. As when he that hath deſerued death, hath his life reſtored vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, but not his libertie, or his goods, or his former Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and dignities.</p>
               <p n="11">11 Pardon alſo, is either free, or merited.</p>
               <p n="12">12 Free pardon is, when the puniſhment of an offence is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted of meere grace, without any ſatisfaction at all.</p>
               <p n="13">13 The more freely a man is pardoned, the leſſe he is iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: And the more a man is iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified, the leſſe freely is he par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned.</p>
               <p n="14">14 Some offences are of that nature, and doe in ſuch a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner wrong the partie offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that without wrong done to himſelfe, and diſparagement to Iuſtice, hee cannot meerely
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:21145:32"/> pardon the ſame.</p>
               <p n="15">15 Pardon merited is, when in ſtead of the ſpeciall euill or puniſhment due to the offence, other ſatisfaction is made.</p>
               <p n="16">16 If that ſatisfaction which is made, bee in it ſelfe as great an euill, or puniſhment to the offender, as that ſpecial euill or puniſhment that he ſhuld haue ſuſtained; Or if the offender be as willing, to vnder-goe the <hi>ſpeciall</hi> puniſhment, as to make other ſatisfaction; there to vrge ſuch a ſatisfaction, is not to pardon.</p>
               <p n="17">17 If by Lawe it be left to the Offenders choyce, whether he wil vndergoe ſuch a ſpeciall puniſhment, or redeeme the ſame, with ſuch or ſuch ſpeciall ſatisfaction; there the offended in accepting of other ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, doth not pardon.</p>
               <p n="18">
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:21145:33"/>18 If that ſatisfaction which is made, how full ſo euer, be in it ſelfe a leſſe euill, to the party offending, then the ſpeciall pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, that hee ſhould haue ſuſtained; If it be in his choice who is offended, whether hee wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> accept the one or the other, there to accept of the ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is in ſome degree to pardon.</p>
               <p n="19">19 He who is vrged to make ſatisfaction in his owne perſon, is leſſe pardoned then he who is ſuffered to ſatisfie by another.</p>
               <p n="20">20 If one cannot make Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction for himſelfe, and if none elſe can, or will make ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction for him, but he that is moſt deare to the partie offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; And where the offence is of that nature, that nothing can ſatisfie for the ſame, but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame puniſhment; And that it is a blot, to the iuſtice of the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:21145:33"/> partie offended, not to puniſh the ſame, and in his free choice, whether hee will puniſh the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender, in his owne perſon, or admit of that Satisfaction ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered by the other; There in this caſe to admit of the others ſatisfaction, and to releaſe the partie offending, from puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is, if not more, yet as gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly and mercifully to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don the offender, as if hee had done it meerly, without any ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction at all.</p>
               <p n="21">21 Where there are diuers perſons equally guiltie, &amp; ſuch a Satisfaction aforeſaide, is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted for ſome, and nor for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſome, and that without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny reſpect of worth in the one, more then in the other, but of the meere and free good will, and pleaſure of him that pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth; there in this reſpect, the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:21145:34"/> pardon (though purchaſed) may be ſaide, to be after a ſort, a free pardon.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> Of Iustification be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore GOD.</head>
               <p n="1">1 HItherto of the Doctrine of Iuſtification in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall. <hi>Iuſtification</hi> (yet more ſpecially) is eyther before God or man.</p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>GOD</hi> beeing infinite in Truth and Knowledge, cannot deceiue or be deceiued. Thoſe therefore, who are iuſtified be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, ſo farre forth as they are iuſtified, they muſt needs be ſome way or other, truely iuſt and righteous; It being equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly an abhomination to him, to iuſtifie the vnrighteous, as to
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:21145:34"/> condemne the righteous. <hi>Prou:</hi> 17.15. <hi>Eſa:</hi> 5.23.</p>
               <p n="3">3 To bee iuſtified before <hi>GOD,</hi> is to be cleared in his ſight, and before his iudgement ſeate, from the guilt of Sinne; And therby abſolued from pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, in diuine Iuſtice due vnto the ſame.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Sinne is a tranſgreſſion of Gods reuealed will. For no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe can bee Sinne, in his ſight, but that which is done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his will, ſufficiently by ſome meanes or other, made knowne.</p>
               <p n="5">5 <hi>GOD</hi> is infinitely and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentially iuſt. And therefore of neceſſitie, his will muſt needes be the abſolute rule of <hi>Iustice.</hi> Whence theſe &amp; ſuch like con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences, are infallibly true; God willeth this or that, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is iuſt: This or that is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:21145:35"/> to his will, therefore it is vniuſt: This or that, he nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther willeth, nor nilleth, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is indifferent. i. Neither iuſt nor vniuſt.</p>
               <p n="6">6 <hi>Iustification</hi> before God, is either by pleading the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ulfilling of the Law, or that which is pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>portionable thereunto.</p>
               <p n="7">7 Thoſe who haue fulfilled the Law, are iuſt in Gods ſight, by their owne inherent righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, &amp; accordingly, if neede require, in that regard, iuſtifia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
               <p n="8">8 In vaine it is, for any man to bee accuſed, or charged be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, eyther for his doing thoſe things, which are accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his Law; or for his not doing at all, thoſe things which he hath done. Neither is there in that regard, any daunger or cauſe to feare any Iudgement
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:21145:35"/> or puniſhment from God, vpon any ſuch charge or accuſation. And therefore, there is no vſe of any ſuch Iuſtification before God, by formall righteouſnes, or the Law.</p>
               <p n="9">9 The Lawe is an exact and perfect rule of Iuſtice, giuen by God, not in ieſt, as though hee cared not whether it were ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued, or no; But in the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt earneſt that euer Lawes were giuen.</p>
               <p n="10">10 The Law of God, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery parcel thereof, is ſo equall and iuſt, and grounded vpon that equitie, that he who ſhall breake the leaſt iot and title thereof, muſt needs in himſelfe be vniuſt in the eyes of God.</p>
               <p n="11">11 Hee that keepeth the whole Lawe exactly, doeth no more in equitie, reaſon, and iuſtice, then he is bound to do;
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:21145:36"/> and hee that tranſgreſſeth the Law but in one iot, doth ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in more wrong and diſhonour to God, then in obſeruing all the reſt, he doth honour him.</p>
               <p n="12">12 The ſeuerall parts of this Law doe ſo conſpire, and are in that manner ſo linked toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, &amp; are of that affinitie and dependa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, that hee who tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſeth any one parte thereof, doth therein in ſome degree or other tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſgreſſe the whole law.</p>
               <p n="13">13 The Law is broken as oft as a man doth any thing that is forbidden, leaueth vndone any thing that is commaunded, or doth any thing commanded in any other manner, or to any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther end then it requireth.</p>
               <p n="14">14 The more that a man by the power and freedome of his owne will and nature keepeth the Law, the more iuſt he is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:21145:36"/> to the Lawe; and the more he keepeth it by ſuperna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall helpe and aſſiſtance, the leſſe iuſt he is, according to the the ſame Law.</p>
               <p n="15">15 That outward obſeruance of ſuch &amp; ſuch parts of the law, as ariſeth from the reſtrayning power of Gods Spirit onely, or through want of power, means, occaſions, or opportunities to the contrary; or vpon ſiniſter ends and reſpects, is no part of of that Iuſtice, which is accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Law.</p>
               <p n="16">16 The puniſhment due to the leaſt breach of the law (and that according to God his moſt iuſt &amp; righteous iudgement) is euerlaſting torment in Hell.</p>
               <p n="17">17 None therefore can be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed inherently iuſt in his ſight, who are guiltie of any ſuch acte, whereby hee is iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:21145:37"/> commaunded in the Lawe; yet their ends and purpoſes therin, are ſiniſter &amp; wicked, and tend ſome way or other, to the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therance of ſome other impiety that is in them. So that their righteouſnes, ſuch as it is, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing well ſcanned) will be found to bee, but weapons and inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, of ſome vnrighteouſnes or other.</p>
               <p n="5">5 All men by nature are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieted, &amp; grieued for nothing ſo much, as that they wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, meanes, and opportunities, to commit ſome ſinne or other.</p>
               <p n="6">6 He which makes moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of obedience to Gods Lawe, doth not that which hee doth, by the power &amp; ſtrength of his owne Nature, but by the powerfull help and aſſiſtance of Gods Spirit, regenerating him, &amp; making him a new creature.</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:21145:37"/>7 The beſt, and moſt righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous man that is, doth in more things tranſgreſſe, then keepe the law of God. Neither do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny keepe it, in ſo many things, or in that degree that they haue power to doe.</p>
               <p n="8">8 Thoſe particular actions, which the beſt men doe in obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the law, are defectiue, and not in all points anſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the Law; but haue Sinne in that manner cleauing vnto them that God in that r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gard, may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſtly reiect the beſt <hi>works,</hi> that are or can be done, by any man in this life.</p>
               <p n="9">9 No mortall m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n therefore, can bee iu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tified before God, by pleading the fulfilling of the Lawe, or any formall inherent righteouſnes of his owne; But the more hee ſhall ſtand there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, the more vniuſt, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:21145:38"/> hee ſhall ſhewe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XI.</hi> ¶ That no man can make Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction for his owne ſinne, or an others.</head>
               <p n="1">1 SEeing no man can be iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by pleading the fulfilling of the Lawe; It followeth, that they who are iuſtified be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, are iuſtified by ſome other proportionable meanes.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Thoſe proportionable meane<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> muſt needes bee, ſome ſpeciall Satisfaction, made for thoſe ſinnes which they haue committed. <hi>Rom:</hi> 3.23.26 24.</p>
               <p n="3">3 It is a ſpeciall blemiſh, to the iuſtice of God, to free a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner from the puniſhment of the Law, except his Iuſtice bee by
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:21145:38"/> ſome meanes or other ſatisfied.</p>
               <p n="4">4 The guilt of ſin meriting at Gods hand, in his iuſt Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, eternal torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts; that ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by which a ſinner is truly iuſtified, muſt needes be ſuch as may fully and ſufficiently, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit freedome from the ſame pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment.</p>
               <p n="5">5 He that ſinneth but once, though afterward by his owne ſtrength, he ſhould in all things fulfill the law of God; yet ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in ſo doing, hee doeth no more then he was bound to do<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk:</hi> 17.10. <hi>Deu:</hi> 5.29. &amp; 6.25. &amp; 12.32.</note> thogh he had not ſinned at all hee cannot by that meanes be ſaide to make any part of ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction; much leſſe if hee ſhall fulfill the ſame, not by his owne power, but by ſpeciall grace &amp; ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ength from God. For the more that God helpeth vs, the more doth hee merit of vs, and
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:21145:39"/> the leſſe wee doe merit of him.</p>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">2. <hi>Cor:</hi> 3.5. <hi>Phil:</hi> 2.15. <hi>Heb:</hi> 13.21. <hi>Ioh:</hi> 15.5.</note>
               <p n="6">6 There is no one good work required by the Law, that any man ſince the fall, is able to do, anſwerable in all reſpects to the Law. And<note n="(a)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſai:</hi> 64.6. <hi>Iob</hi> 9.2.3.15.20.21. <hi>Rom</hi> 7.18.22.</note> therefore the beſt works required by the law as they be done by man, cannot iuſtifie himſelf, much leſſe make Satisfaction for any ſinne.</p>
               <p n="7">7 The Law of God bindeth all men, to<note n="(a)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Deu:</hi> 6.5. <hi>Matt:</hi> 22.31.</note> loue the Lord with all their heart, ſoule, and ſtrength; And therefore alſo to the vttermoſt of their power, to glorifie him. There cannot then be deuiſed, any worke ſo great, tending to<note n="(b)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Col:</hi> 1.11. <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.8.</note> Gods glory, but the Lawe by ſome circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtance
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:21145:39"/> or other bindeth men therevn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</p>
               <p n="8">8 Therefore, there can bee no workes of ſupererogation, greater or worthier, then thoſe which are required in the Law, by which a man can, either in whole or in part, make any Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to God for ſin. Yea, there is nothing that a man can doe, in honor and worſhip vnto him, which is ſo much as accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table vnto him, except himſelfe require it in his word.</p>
               <p n="9">9 Seeing euery ſinne, in the moſt iuſt and righteous iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God, deſerueth euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting torment in Hell-fire; there is nothing that any man can ſuffer, eyther in this life, or afterward, which may be mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured by time, which can either in whole or in part, make Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:21145:40" rendition="simple:additions"/> for ſinne; there beeing no proportion, betweene that which is Euerlaſting, and the longeſt time that can be imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. <hi>Rom:</hi> 3.9. <hi>&amp;</hi> 6 23. <hi>Gal:</hi> 3.10. 2. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.8. <hi>Mat:</hi> 25.46.</p>
               <p n="10">10 No man ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> plead he hath ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred any wrong, (much leſſe any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>) at Gods ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, whereby hee deſerues to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitted for the leaſt ſinne.</p>
               <p n="10">10 No man therefore, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by any deeds, or ſufferings of his owne, can poſſibly, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in whole or in parte, make Satisfaction for the leaſt of his ſins. And therfore, ſuch as are iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified before God, muſt needs be accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted righteous, by that which is formally in ſom other.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XII.</hi> That no other meere Creature, can make Satisfaction for ſinne.</head>
               <p n="1">1 SEeing no Sinner can ſatisfie
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:21145:40"/> the iuſtice of God for his ſinne, by any righteouſneſſe or ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of his owne, either he muſt (thogh guilty but of one ſinne) according to the iuſt Iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of God, be eternally damned; or hee muſt needs make Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction by ſome other perſon.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Though there were but one ſinner in the world, and all the reſt were iuſt and righteous perſons; yet there is nothing that all they either ſeuerally or ioyntly, or with the helpe of all the Saints and Angells in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen could do or ſuffer, that can ſatisfie the Iuſtice of God for that ſinner, though hee were guilty but of the leaſt ſin; It be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not poſſible that creatures being finite, ſhould ſatisfie ſo infinite a wrath and Iuſtice.</p>
               <p n="3">3 He therefore, that will be found able indeed to make any
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:21145:41"/> ſuch ſatisfaction, as ſhall truely iuſtifie a ſinner, in that manner that hee ſhall ſeeme in the eyes of God, as a righteous perſon, and vnworthy of the condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation aforeſaide, muſt needes not onely be perfitly righteous himſelfe, but Infinite alſo, and Almighty, and by conſequent true God. <hi>Eſa:</hi> 63. <hi>Heb:</hi> 1.2.6.</p>
               <p n="4">4 God being but one, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not properly be ſatisfied meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by himſelf, or by any act, that is meerely and abſolutely a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine act: for in ſuch a manner to ſatisfie himſelf, is in effect meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to forgiue without ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and to pardon without any <hi>Iustification</hi> at all.</p>
               <p n="5">5 The perſon then who is to make ſuch a Satisfaction, muſt not only be God, but ſome way or other alſo different fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God, and<note n="(a)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Ro:</hi> 1.3. <hi>Gal:</hi> 4.1.</note> therfore, and in that reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:21145:41"/>
                  <note n="(b)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Ioh:</hi> 14.28.</note> inferior to God.</p>
               <p n="6">6 It paſſeth the wit of men or Angells to finde out ſuch a perſon: ſo that if an hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bled ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſhould be left to himſelfe to ſearch out this myſtery, the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he ſhould wade therin, the more he ſhould plunge himſelfe into a bottomleſſe gulfe of hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror and deſpaire.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 13.</hi> ¶ That the Sonne of God is he that hath made Satisfaction for the Sinnes of all them that ſhall be Iustified.</head>
               <p n="1">1 GOD in the Goſpell hath reuealed ſuch a perſon, as is both willing &amp; able to make full Satisfaction for ſinne, and
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:21145:42"/> therby to procure the iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a ſinner before God, and a perfect Reconciliation.</p>
               <p n="2">2. This perſon is <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> the<note n="(a)" place="bottom">1. <hi>Tim:</hi> 2.5. <hi>Rom:</hi> 3, 24.25.</note> onely begotten Son of God,<note n="(b)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Iohn.</hi> 1.14.18.3.16.18.</note> the ſecond perſon in Trinity.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Thoſe therefore who are iuſtified by Satiſfaction made by him, muſt of neceſſity bee righteous before God, by that righteouſnes, which is formally in Chriſt onely. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.20.24. <hi>&amp;</hi> 4.5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 10.3.4.5.6.9. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.8.9. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.21.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The Son of God, to the end that hee might make full ſatisfaction for the ſins of ſome men, did take vpon himſelfe the guilt of their Sinns. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.21. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 53.12. <hi>&amp;</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.3. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.24. Typed, <hi>Leu.</hi> 4.
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:21145:42"/> 4.24.29.33. with 5.5.16. <hi>Exod.</hi> 29.10.9. <hi>Leu.</hi> 8.14.22. <hi>&amp;</hi> 16.1.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Hauing taken vpon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe the guilt of Sin, and being. not fit as hee was God, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme any true Satisfactory worke hee becam<note n="(a)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Iohn.</hi> 1.14. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.7. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.4.</note> man, alſo, aſſuming<note n="(b)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.14.16.</note> into the perſon of his diety, the nature of man, and ſo became<note n="(c)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.13.16. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 3.13.</note> in one and the ſame Perſon true God, and true man, &amp; thereby a fit mediatour<note n="(d)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.5. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.13. <hi>Phil.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.5.</note> betweene God and<note n="(e)" place="bottom">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.5. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.13.</note> man, that ſo by the Power<note n="(f)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.14. <hi>&amp;</hi> 10.5.15.</note> of his diuine nature hee might make full Satiſfaction, in and by the humane Nature.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:21145:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>6 By this meanes he became in reſpect of his humane Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture aſſumed, inferior vnto God, and a Seruant bound vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that law, which (by their Creation) all other men are bound vnto, and owing in that regard, both vnto God and man, the very ſame ſeruices and duties that are therin vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally required of all men, and ſubiect to the very ſame curſes and iudgements, that vpon the not performing of them, all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men are ſubiect vnto.</p>
               <p n="7">7 The Hypoſtaticall vnion of the humane nature of Chriſt, into the perſon of the Deity, doth no more free him from the bond of the aforeſaid law, whilſt he conuerſt vpon Earth, then it makes him ceaſe to bee true man. And as notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the ſaid vnion, the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:21145:43" rendition="simple:additions"/> of <hi>CHRIST,</hi> beeing a true humane bodie, was ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to corruption, and needed for it ſelfe, meate, drinke, &amp;c: So his Soule, being a humane ſoule, and ſo (notwithſtanding the ſaide vnion) remaining; that vnion cannot bee ſaid to free it from the neceſſary obſeruance of that law, wherein the true formall naturall and eſſentiall righteouſnes of a humane ſoule doth conſiſt.</p>
               <p n="8">8. And as hee was ſtrictly and abſolutely bound vnto the aforeſaid law euen as much as any other man, ſo hee did moſt accurately and preciſely fulfill the ſame, denying no obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence vnto God, which the ſaid law did require, but perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing al things commanded; and that not only (as the Schooles vſe to ſpeak) materially, but for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mally
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:21145:44" rendition="simple:additions"/> alſo, by meanes wherof hee was (as man, truly and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly righteous in all things according to the law of Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p n="9">9. This obſeruing of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall law being the work<note n="(a)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Eſa:</hi> 42.1.53.11.</note> of a Seruant,<note n="(b)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Phil:</hi> 2.7.</note> a part of his humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation, a meanes wherby hee declared himſelfe inferior to his father, and<note n="(c)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Luk:</hi> 2.20.</note> which hee did to pleaſe his father, &amp; by which hee was the more accepted of God; Some part thereof bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing directly<note n="(d)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Gal:</hi> 4.4.</note> a part of his mediation, as his earneſt pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, Euery part therof being of that nature,<note n="(e)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Eſa:</hi> 53.9.10.11. 1. <hi>Corint:</hi> 5.21. <hi>Hebr:</hi> 7.26. 1. <hi>Pet:</hi> 2.22.24. <hi>&amp;</hi> 18.9. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3.18. <hi>&amp;</hi> 1. <hi>Ioh:</hi> 3.5.</note> that without the ſame no other ſatiſfaction could haue beene auaileable, or effectuall, and all proceeding from ſuch an eſtate and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as hee needd not haue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergone (nor had not) if he had
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:21145:44" rendition="simple:additions"/> not taken vpon him, to ſatisfie for ſinners; ſome part of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction which hee made muſt needs conſiſt therein, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it muſt in ſome degree or other bee imputed to them to their <hi>Iuſtification.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">10 As hee who to ſatisfie for another, becomes a Slaue to men; doeth in and by all thoſe actes, which the Lawes binde a Slaue vnto, make ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, yea thogh they be ſuch acts, as hee be comming a ſlaue, is bound vpon pain of death to vndergo: So ſeeing <hi>CHRIST,</hi> onely that he might ſatisfie for <hi>Sinners,</hi> did becom <hi>Man,</hi> which is a greater debaſement to him
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:21145:45"/> (being <hi>GOD,</hi> equal to the <hi>FA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THER,</hi>) then if the Sonne of a Prince ſhould become a ſlaue, it muſt needs be, that in and by thoſe acts which he was bound vnto by Gods Lawe, as a man, (though beeing man, hee was bound vnto them, vnder paine of eternall damnation) he made ſome degree of Satisfaction or other: and therefore, it muſt needes be alſo in ſome meaſure or other, a part of that righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſnes, in and by the imputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whereof, a ſinner is iuſtified; and in this caſe, the greater the bond was that he did vndergoe for the doing of them, the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was his merit.</p>
               <p n="11">11 Therefore his very aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of our humane Nature, and all the obedience he yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded thereupon, and by reaſon thereof, whilſt hee was vpon
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:21145:45"/> earth, at leaſt in the ſtate of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation, euen during the time of his priuate life, ſeeme to bee ſome part and beginning of the actuall execution of his Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Office, by meanes whereof, in part hee pacified GOD, and conſequently, in part ſatisfied for ſinne.</p>
               <p n="12">12 Thogh at his Baptiſme he was ſolemnly declared to bee that <hi>Meſſias,</hi> and though after that hee did more ſpecially ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt himſelfe to be the <hi>Meſſias</hi> by his publicke Miniſtery: yet it appeares not by any probable reaſon, that then (and not till then) he began actually to doe the works of a Mediator.</p>
               <p n="13">13 As Chriſt was borne of a Woman, not for his owne ſake, but for theirs whoſe Sauiour &amp; Redeemer he is: So being born of a Woman, he was made vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:21145:46"/> the Lawe alſo, not for his owne cauſe, but for ours; yea, therfore he was borne of a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, that ſo for our ſake hee might be vnder the Law. Alſo as he became a Seruant for our ſake; So in that very regard hee came vnder the Lawe of a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, it being all one to become a Seruant, and to be made vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law of a Seruant; the being vnder the Law of a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, being that which makes him become a Seruant.</p>
               <p n="14">14 Chriſt might haue been a pure, holy, harmeleſſe, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defiled High-prieſt, though hee had performed no other obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the Morall Lawe, nor had beene no otherwiſe (in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of his obedience to the ſaid Law) a Seruant, then hee is now being glorified: So much therefore of his conformitie to
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:21145:46" rendition="simple:additions"/> the ſaid Lawe as concernes his humiliation, muſt either be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary, or part of his ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
               <p n="15">15 Though this obedience of Chriſt to the Law bee a part of that righteouſnes whereby a ſinner is iuſtified; yet it follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not thence that a ſinner is iuſtified by the works of the Law, in any ſuch ſenſe, as they are<note n="(a)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.20.28. <hi>&amp;</hi> 4.2. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.16. <hi>&amp;</hi> 10.11.12.</note> excluded by the Apoſtle, Seeing the Lawe bindeth euery man to doe the works required therein, in<note n="(b)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 27.26. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 8.14. <hi>Leu.</hi> 18.5. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.5. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.12.</note> his own perſon &amp; not by a Deputie. And the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle directly diſputeth onely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſuch a iuſtification by the Law, whereby a man<note n="(c)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.2.4. <hi>&amp;</hi> 10.3.</note> fanci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth by his owne deedes done in his owne perſon to be iuſtified: For, though Chriſt himſelfe, who in his own perſon fulfilled the Law, may be iuſtified by the
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:21145:47"/> ſame Law; yet it followeth not that they to whom this righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes is imputed, are iuſtified thereby,<note n="(d)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.21. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.27.</note> but rather the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary:</p>
               <p n="16">16. This l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gall righteouſnes of our Sauiour Chriſt cannot truely be ſaid to be totally im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to euery ſinner that is iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified: for then there needed no other or further ſatisfaction to be made; ſeeing by meanes thereof alone euery ſuch ſinner muſt needes bee as it were per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly righteous; and where a man is ſo reputed, there needes no ſatisfaction to be made: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can any one ſpeciall or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct part be ſayd to be impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:21145:47" rendition="simple:additions"/> to one, and another part thereof to another: but it is as a Diamond or Iewell, payd for the ſatisfaction of many mens debts, which cannot bee ſaide that it is either totally paid, for euery debter, or one part for one, and another for another; but generally, the whole is paid for all, and euery one hath his part in the whole; and not one in this part of it, and another in that.</p>
               <p n="17">17 Chriſt yeelded full obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, not onely to the Morall Lawe, by meanes whereof hee was perfectly righteous, and as man needed no other or further degree of righteouſnes: but he ſubmitted himſelfe alſo to thoſe Lawes which were<note n="(a)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Gal</hi> 4.4.</note> peculiar to Gods people, and preſcribed to them by occaſion of ſin, and in conforming whereunto they
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:21145:48"/> profeſſed themſelues to be ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; and which, had they not beene ſinners, they ſhould ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer haue beene ſubiect vnto; as if by this careful and ſtrict con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming thereunto, hee<note n="(b)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Eſa.</hi> 53.12.</note> had acknowledged himſelfe the chiefe of ſinners: hence he was<note n="(c)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 2.21.</note> Circumcized,<note n="(d)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 2.24.</note> Offered Oblations,<note n="(e)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 7.2.10. <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.17.18.19.20.</note> performed all other Ceremoniall Obſeruan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Hence he was alſo<note n="(f)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.13. <hi>Luk.</hi> 3.21.</note> Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized,<note n="(g)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.26.</note> and receiued the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of his owne Bodie &amp; Bloud: and<note n="(h)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.10.</note> this alſo he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth expreſly a part of his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes.</p>
               <p n="18">18 Hee being without any ſinne of his owne, he could not
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:21145:48" rendition="simple:additions"/> as man bee bounde vnto theſe kinde of Lawes: his obedience therefore vnto them muſt needs be either of no vſe, or elſe muſt be performed in regard of our ſinnes imputed vnto him. And therefore whatſoeuer hee did herein, it was principally for the expiation of them, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently for our iuſtification.</p>
               <p n="19">19 Our Sauiour tooke not onely our Nature vpon him, and ſubiected himſelf to the Lawes before ſaid, but together with our Nature all the common<note n="(a)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.3. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.17.18. <hi>&amp;</hi> 4.15.</note> frailties and infirmities thereof. Hee framed not therefore vnto himſelfe at the firſt a glorious body like vnto <hi>Abſolons,</hi> or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Adams</hi> in the firſt Creation; but hee was (though<note n="(b)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 1.18. <hi>Luke</hi> 1.34.35.</note> mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culouſly by the power of the holy Ghoſt, without the helpe of man) conceiued in the womb
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:21145:49"/> of a weake and ſinfull woman. After tenne moneths hee was brought into the World, after the manner of other children, and with all the common weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes and infirmities of other children. And hee was ſubiect vnto, and indured in his fleſh before he was glorified,<note n="(d)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 4.2. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.6.7.</note> hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, thirſt, heat, cold, weariſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, &amp;c.</p>
               <note n="(c)" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.6.</note>
               <p n="20">20 Though notwithſtanding the aforeſaid aſſuming of the humane Nature, and the frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties thereof, hee continued ſtill to be God, equall with his Father, yet hee was in this Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane nature of his further con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, ſo to debaſe himſelf, as to indure whilſt he was vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> earth, for ſundry yeares, many miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:21145:49"/> and calamities, &amp; to beare, and put vp at the hands of men,<note n="(b)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Ioh:</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>3.8. <hi>Mar.</hi> 14.45, <hi>Luke</hi> 22.34. <hi>Matth:</hi> 26.74. <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 14.27.</note> euen of thoſe which were his owne ſpeciall Officers and Seruants, many horrible intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable in dignities &amp; contume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, as though he had bene the moſt vnworthy, baſe, &amp; conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tible perſon, that euer the earth bore. More particularly, hee was content to the ende afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaide, amongſt other abuſes, to be moſt, wrongfully<note n="(c)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.60.61.65. <hi>Mar.</hi> 1.14.64. <hi>Lu.</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.65. <hi>&amp;</hi> 23. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> accuſed, arraigned, and condemned, of high blaſphemie and Treaſon, and in that iudgment, not only moſt<note n="(d)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Mar:</hi> 14.65: <hi>Luke</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 65.64. <hi>Mar:</hi> 15.15. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 19.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> inhumanely, and barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly, to be buffeted, ſpet vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whipped, Crowned with Thorns, but alſo to bee put vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the<note n="(e)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Ioh:</hi> 19.18. <hi>Gal.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.13. <hi>Phil:</hi> 2.8.</note> moſt ſhamefull and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed death of the Croſſe; A death <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> none were put vnto, but the baſeſt and moſt odious
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:21145:50"/> malefactors, ſuch a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> were repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the moſt notorious villains in a State: yea, ſuch as were af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a ſort, in ſome ſpeciall man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner accurſed of God himſelfe.</p>
               <p n="21">21 All this was not ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Redemption and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of ſinners, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>es <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> moſt patient enduring of all theſe indignities from men; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> hee hanged vppon the accurſed Tree) had ſuch a deepe ſenſe of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſible wrath of God his F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:21145:50"/> and of his dreadfull iuſtice againſt thoſe ſinnes, the Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction whereof hee had taken vpon himſelfe, that the very ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion thereof (before it ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vpon him) made him ſweate drops of bloud. And the ſenſe thereof when it was vppon his Soule, made him moſt fearefully to crie out and ſay, <hi>My God, my God, why hast thou forſaken mee?</hi> And all this hee<note n="(b)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Eſa.</hi> 53.7 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.7. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 9.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>6.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Rom.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> endured, till the iuſtice of God was fully ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied for their ſinnes, the guilt wherof he had taken vpon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,</p>
               <p n="22">22 In th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe things thus none and ſuffred ioyntly conſiſts that Righteouſnes, or Satisfaction of Chriſtian<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; by which a ſinner is iuſtified before God; Though
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:21145:51"/> the Scripture principally attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes the Saluation, Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Iuſtification of a ſinner, to his ſufferings on the Croſſe, and his Bloud-ſhedding, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in them conſiſted the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummation</hi> of his Prieſtly Office, and the maine, &amp; principall, and moſt effectuall part of his Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction.</p>
               <p n="23">23 Theſe things aforeſaide being done and ſuffred by ſuch a perſon, muſt needes be of<note n="(a)" place="bottom">1. <hi>Cor:</hi> 6.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0. <hi>&amp;</hi> 7.23. 1. <hi>Pet:</hi> 1.19.</note> ineſtimable price, and in that regard as much (if not more) glorifie the Iuſtice<note n="(b)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Rom:</hi> 3.26.</note> of God, as if the Sinners themſelues either had neuer ſinned, or had made full Satisfaction in their owne perſons.</p>
               <p n="24">24 They may be ſufficient for the <hi>Iuſtification</hi> of a Sinner, and
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:21145:51"/> may be ſaid to be imputed ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto, though euery particular Sinner be not eſteemed and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to haue done and ſuffred thoſe very particulars, which Chriſt herein both did, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred, it being ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that they were vndertaken for<note n="(a)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Rom:</hi> 5.8.9.10. 1. <hi>Cor:</hi> 5.7. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20.</note> a ſinner, and accepted of God, either for that righteouſnes which ſhould haue inhered in a Sinner, or for that Satisfaction that the ſinner ſhould haue made in his owne perſon</p>
               <p n="25">25 Thoſe for whom Chriſt Ieſus hath in manner aforeſaide ſatisfied, are eſteemed in Gods eyes, in regard of that Satisfac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion made, as if they were free from<note n="(a)" place="bottom">1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.9. <hi>Apo:</hi> 1.5</note>
               </p>
               <p n="26">26 No Sinner can be eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:21145:52"/> free from all ſinne in man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner aforeſaid; but he muſt ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in of neceſſitie hee eſteemed, as<note n="(a)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Rom:</hi> 4.5.6.8. <hi>&amp;.</hi> 5.19. <hi>Phil:</hi> 3.9. 2. <hi>Cor:</hi> 5.21.</note> perfectly righteous, the leaſt defect of righteouſnes, being a degree of Sinne.</p>
               <p n="27">27 It is therefore all one, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> from all ſinne, and to be perfectly righteous; That (ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) by Chriſts ſuffering<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wee are fre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d from all ſinnes, and by his Actiue obedience, wee are made righteous, (as thogh theſe were two diuers effects of thoſe diuers actes) ſeemes to haue no warrant from Scripture, and to be repugna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to reaſon; It being not poſſible to deuiſe a <hi>medium</hi> between him that is no Sinner, &amp; a righteous perſon, no more then between the Ayer free fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> degree of darknes and fullie
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:21145:52" rendition="simple:additions"/> light, or a man in no meaſure blinde, and perfectly ſeeing.</p>
               <p n="28">28 Hee that is free from all ſinne, is thereby freede from all degrees of eternall death: and whatſoeuer doth effectually &amp; meritoriouſly free a man from all degrees of death, doth alſo thereby in title a man to euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life, Chriſts ſufferings therefore, and his righteouſnes muſt either ioyntly doe both, or one of them muſt be vtterly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both; for that which effecteth the one, effecteth the other alſo of neceſſitie.</p>
               <p n="29">29 Though it be ſaid, <hi>That Christ dyed for our ſinnes, and roſe againe for our iustification:</hi> yet it doth not follow thence, that by his death and ſuffering only our ſinnes are expiated, and by his fulfilling the Law, we ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer made righteous, and inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:21145:53" rendition="simple:additions"/> to euerlaſting life: for by his reſurrection in that place we cannot vnderſtand his fulfilling the Law, it being no part there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and his dying for ſin, was for our iuſtification alſo: ſo that the meaning of the Apoſtle ſeemes to bee this onely: That Chriſt both dyed for our ſinnes, and roſe againe to this end; that we might be iuſtified, implying al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, that though Chriſt dyed for our ſins, yet if hee had not riſen againe, we ſhould not haue bin iuſtified.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIIII.</hi> Of the Pardon of our ſinnes, and our Adoption.</head>
               <p n="1">1 THe ſatisfaction aforeſaid being made by Chriſt, it muſt needes be effectuall, and
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:21145:53" rendition="simple:additions"/> not in vaine, and therefore the plenary pardon of all their ſins, for whom he ſatisfied, muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily follow thereupon; for if but one ſinne be vnpardoned, eternall death and miſery muſt neceſſarily ſucceede.</p>
               <p n="2">2 It had beene a ſtaine and blot to the iuſtice of GOD, to haue meerely pardoned the ſins of any without due ſatisfaction made; elſe wee muſt hold, that either the ſufferings of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour were not ſuch as they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, but onely deluſions, which is blaſphemie for any to imagine, or that GOD would neuer haue ſuffered his Sonne to haue indured that which hee did.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Though the pardon of ſin was bought with a more valu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able price then euer any thing elſe was, or can be bought; yet
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:21145:54" rendition="simple:additions"/> in that God accepted of ſuch a price as this at the hands of his only begotten Sonne, in whom hee was well pleaſed, for them that were his enemies, and in whoſe eternall confuſion hee might haue glorified himſelfe, hee doeth therein as graciouſly and mercifully pardon vs, as if hee had done it freely, without any price at all: yea, the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſatisfaction was, the more was his mercy and grace, in pardoning by ſuch a means.</p>
               <p n="4">4 There is not the leaſt me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite &amp; deſert in thoſe for whom God accepteth the aforeſaid ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, why they ſhould be pardoned any more then the damned, vnto whome God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyeth this pardon. God there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (when hee might, with ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour &amp; glory haue damned all) ſo freely accepting ſuch a ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:21145:54"/> for ſome, without any cauſe in themſelues, may be ſaid in that reſpect moſt freely to pardon them.</p>
               <p n="5">5 Though the eſtate of a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner that is iuſtified, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently pardoned, in it ſelfe conſidered, bee for the preſent in this life many degrees worſe then it ſhould haue beene, if he had not ſinned at all; yet, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the certaine poſſibilitie to the inheritance of heauen, and the eternall glory thereof at the<note n="(a)" place="bottom">8.17. <hi>&amp;</hi> 18.19.29.30. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.17.18. <hi>&amp;</hi> 5.1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.2.4.</note> end of this ſhort life, it farre excelleth the other:</p>
               <p n="6">6 The<note n="(a)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.15.17. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4.</note> inheritance of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and our ſpeciall title to be the<note n="(b)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.12. 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.1.</note> Sonnes of God, being a condition in it ſelfe many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees greater then that which we loſt by ſinne, we cannot be
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:21145:55"/> ſo properly ſaide to receiue all the degrees therof by vertue of any act, either of iuſtification or pardon; it being in the nature of the one, to f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ee onely from fault, and of the other, to free from puniſhment deſerued by the fault: in which regard, as the partie by vertue of them muſt needes be placed, either in the ſame, or as good an eſtate as he was in before: ſo more then this cannot bee required by vertue of either.</p>
               <p n="7">7 Though we cannot be ſaid to bee intituled to that ſpeciall Adoption of Sonnes, and all the degrees of glory in heauen by the merits and ſatisfaction of Chriſt aforeſaid, ſo farre foorth as they are applyed to our iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication: yet ſeeing Chriſtes
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:21145:55"/> merits may bee greater, and of more force then for the ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction for ſinne, and the meere iuſtification of ſinners thereby, wee may notwithſtanding bee ſaide to bee both adopted and glorified by his merits; It being cleere, That all the grace &amp; glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie which wee ſhall inioy<note n="(a)" place="bottom">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.21-24. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.5, 6. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.13. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.12.</note> is giuen for Chriſts ſake, and by<note n="(b)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.26. <hi>with</hi> 4.4, 5. <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.29.</note> vertue of his mediation, and conſequently of his merits.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XV.</hi> Of Iuſtifying Faith.</head>
               <p n="1">1 THoſe ſinners onely are iuſtified before God, in manner afore-ſaid, who (liuing till they come to yeeres
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:21145:56"/> of diſcretion) doe by a ſound and liuely faith lay hold of and relye vpon the aforeſaid ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction onely, &amp; the merits there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and not vpon any merits &amp; works of their owne.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Hence this faith is called by Diuines, <hi>Iuſtifying Faith,</hi> in which regard alſo men are ſaid to be<note n="(a)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.24.25.30. <hi>&amp;</hi> 10.10. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.8.24. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.8.</note> Iuſtified by faith; and faith is ſaid to<note n="(b)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.3, 5, 6, 9.11.22, 23, 24. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.6. <hi>Iam.</hi> 2.22. <hi>Gen.</hi> 5.6.</note> be accounted for righteouſnes, and to bee<note n="(c)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.27, 28. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.16.</note> that which onely iuſtifieth.</p>
               <p n="3">3 This Faith is a ſpeciall<note n="(a)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Eph:</hi> 2.8. <hi>Phil:</hi> 1.19. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.1.</note> gift of God, giuen onely to the Elect: and therefore the greater it is, the more it bindeth vs to God, &amp; cannot merite at Gods hand any thing for vs: whence
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:21145:56"/> it cannot ſatisfie the iuſtice of God, or merite pardon for the leaſt ſinne, &amp; therfore in proper ſpeech it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be ſaid to iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie a ſinner, or adde, in it ſelfe any true force or efficacy thervnto, it being no meritorious cauſe thereof.</p>
               <p n="4">4 For this cauſe then Faith is ſaide to iuſtifie, and onely to iuſtifie, becauſe it alone is the inſtrument, which apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth and applyeth that righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, for and by the imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion whereof a Sinner is iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed<note n="(a)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Rom:</hi> 3.25.24. <hi>&amp;</hi> 4.24.25. <hi>&amp;</hi> 5.1.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5 Hence it is that the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant of grace in ſteed of that righteouſnes of the Law, which is wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting in vs by reaſon of our ſinne, requireth no other thing inher<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in vs in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:21145:57"/> whereby wee may be decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to bee iuſtified, but Faith onely<note n="(a)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.5.6.9.10. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.14.15.16.18.36. <hi>&amp;</hi> 5.24. <hi>&amp;</hi> 6.40. <hi>Marc:</hi> 16.16. <hi>Act.</hi> 10.43. <hi>&amp;</hi> 16.31.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. It is all one in trueth to ſay, that a ſinner is iuſtified on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the righteouſnes of Chriſt imputed, and that he is iuſtified by Faith: For he only can ſay, hee is iuſtified by Chriſts righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes, who hath Faith: &amp; he who hath Faith, is therfore ſaid to bee iuſtified by Faith alone, becauſe Faith alone apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth and applieth the ſaid righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes: ſo that the one euer implyeth or preſuppoſeth the other.</p>
               <p n="7">7 Repentance and good works doe neceſſarily followe Faith, and according to the degrees of their ſoundnes and ſincerity,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:21145:57"/> they may be of force to iuſtifie either themſelues, or that faith, from which they proceede, but they can haue no force by any merit to iuſtifie a Sinner, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of any ſinne that hee hath committed, though they may ſerue as ſeales and pledges, and ſo many teſtimonies of that iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification which is by Faith in Chriſt alone.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVI.</hi> ¶ Of Iustification before Man.</head>
               <p n="1">1 HItherto of <hi>Iuſtification</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God. Iuſtification beefore Man is, when in any of the forms before ſpoken of, in generall, a perſon is iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied before Man.</p>
               <p n="2">2 A man may after a ſort be iuſtified before men, who in the knowledge of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is moſt vniuſt, and he may be condemned be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:21145:58"/> me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who is known to be (in reſpect of that mater, for which hee is condemned) moſt righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. Alſo a man may be iuſtified before men, for that for which hee ſhall be condemned before God: &amp; he may be iuſtified be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, for that, for which he is condemned of men.</p>
               <p n="3">3 He is vniuerſally iuſtified before the ſtricteſt <hi>Tribunalls</hi> of men, who cannot be proued to haue done any faulte, or who is prooued to bee guiltie of ſuch faults only as all men vniuerſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are guiltie of; This beeing a ſufficient <hi>Plea,</hi> at any humane barre (to free fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all blame and puniſhment amongſt men) that he is therein, no more, nor in no greater degree guiltie, then his Iudges &amp; Accuſers, or the beſt, or all the men in the world. It being inhumane, &amp; conſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:21145:58"/> vniuſt for any man, eyther to accuſe or condemne his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, for that which all, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore himſelfe, and thoſe who care better then himſelfe, are knowne to be guiltie of.</p>
               <p n="4">4 A man euen in that eſtate which he is now in, may ſo liue amongſt men, as he may merit to be (as is aforeſaid) vniuerſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly iuſtified in their Courts, and that eyther by his formall and inherent righteouſneſſe, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe: <hi>Luke</hi> 1.6. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.2. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.15.</p>
               <p n="5">5 A man may ſo treſpaſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a man, that hee can neuer by any means make him full ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, for the fault done, in which caſe hee muſt neceſſarily liue and dye vniuſtified before man.</p>
               <p n="6">6 The extreameſt ſatisfaction that man is to exact of man for
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:21145:59"/> the greateſt fault, is Temporary death: and to wiſh, much more to attempt his eternall death, though for the greateſt treſpaſſe that can bee offered, is greater, and more barbarous crueltie, then is to be found amongſt the Caniballs: and is a greater treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe againſt his neighbour, then any that his neighbor can com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit againſt him in another kind.</p>
               <p n="7">7 Man may bee iuſtified be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Man, not by Man only, but by God alſo.</p>
               <p n="8">8 God alſo may iuſtifie vs before Man by our formall and inherent righteouſnes. Thus by ſundry meanes here vpon earth hee ſometimes iuſtifies his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren againſt the ſundry calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niations and flaunders of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men: But more ſpecially he wil do it at the day of Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in the face of the whole
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:21145:59"/> world; manifeſting, not onely that righteouſneſſe of theirs, which they haue in and by Chriſt; but the inherent inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, integrity, &amp; ſynceritie of their hearts and waies, ſo much belied &amp; traduced by the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked enemies of ſanctifie and Religion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:21145:60"/>
               <head>¶ The Summe of all.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>1</hi> ALl Men are ſinners.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>2</hi> The least ſinne in the iuſt Iudgement of God merits eternall death.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>3</hi> No ſinner can in Gods iuſtice be freede from the ſame, but hee that is truly iuſtified before God.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>4</hi> No ſinner can be iuſtified before God, but by Satisfaction.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>5</hi> No ſinner <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> himſelfe, or any other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>tisfaction.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>6</hi> When <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>re could, Chriſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> God did make Satis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ction.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>7</hi> Chriſt, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ight make ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction became Man.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>8</hi> Chriſt being Man, made ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction by fulfilling the Lawe and dying.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>9</hi> Chriſt hauing made this ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, the Father imputeth it, the holy Ghoſt ſealeth and ratifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:21145:60"/> it to the partie iuſtified.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>10</hi> In ratifying and ſealing it, faith is giuen to beleeue, and appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend it.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>11</hi> Faith being giuen to beleeue &amp; apprehend it, it bringeth forth good workes in teſtification of thankefulneſſe for it.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>1</hi>—God the Father Iuſtifieth by imputation.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>2</hi>—God the Sonne, by Satisfying and Meriting.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>3</hi>—God the Holy Ghost, by Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and Confirming it.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>5</hi>—All three by gratious pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and abſoluing.</item>
                  <item>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>—Faith, by apprehending and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>6</hi>—Good workes, by manifeſting and decl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ring.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>1.</hi> The whole Trinitie are the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall &amp; Efficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t cauſe of iuſtificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>2.</hi> Faith the Inſtrumentall.</item>
                  <pb n="96" facs="tcp:21145:61"/>
                  <item>
                     <hi>3.</hi> Christs Satisfactory Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes the Materiall.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>4.</hi> The Importation therof, the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>5.</hi> The Saluation of a Sinner, the Finall.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>6.</hi> Good workes the effect and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Conſequent.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Ergo,</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>1.</hi> All that are iuſtified, are iusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied onely by the free grace of God, and merites of Chriſt.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>2.</hi> None are iuſtified for, or by, their owne workes.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>3.</hi> None are iuſtified without works.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:21145:61"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
